<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Wajdi Jomaa</title>
    <link>/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Wajdi Jomaa</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Decorator Pattern</title>
      <link>/posts/designpatterns/decorator/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/designpatterns/decorator/</guid>
      <description>Design Patterns If you are currently working on a big programming project, and you feel that your code is insufficient, not reusable, or not readable, or you have the pain to add new features, it&amp;rsquo;s probably the time to take a break and learn about design patterns.
Design patterns will help you to write your code in a scalable and readable way and will make your software better, sometimes a small design choice in your code would save you hours or days of work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Observer Pattern</title>
      <link>/posts/designpatterns/observer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/designpatterns/observer/</guid>
      <description>Observer design pattern Scenario We have a weather for mobile and desktop that displays weather info, but we have a problem that our application is displaying only static data, so we want to connect our application to an API to have up-to-date data,
for this, we have a weather API that grabs different information about the weather
To connect the API to our application in a way that each time the data changes the UI should be updated on both mobile and desktop</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strategy Pattern</title>
      <link>/posts/designpatterns/strategy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/designpatterns/strategy/</guid>
      <description>Strategy Design pattern Scenario GameCo is a company that is planning to build the next-generation fighting game, they need your help to design the application, each character should be able to choose between any style of weapon, and should be able to change the weapon type at runtime
You have the following code:
abstract class fighter(){ private String name; private int health; /// you have to add a weapon to each the fighter class  /// seters and geters  } all characters will extend the fighter class but you need to find a way to add a weapon to each character let&amp;rsquo;s say that we have 2 types of weapons a rifle and a shotgun each one has a method of fire and speed</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Odin project foundation</title>
      <link>/posts/odinproject-foundation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/odinproject-foundation/</guid>
      <description>Odin Project Foundation About the course Odin project Foundation is a completely free course, to learn the fundamentals of HTML, CSS, Javascript. For each topic, the course has different articles or youtube videos and sometimes some exercises and projects.
The Introduction The course starts with some lessons about motivation, managing your time for example &amp;ldquo;Pomodoro&amp;rdquo;, and how to ask questions. also it makes sure you understand how the web works and the meaning of some words like the Internet, HTTP, Browser, Frontend, Website, Webpage&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>folderOrganizer</title>
      <link>/posts/folder_organizer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/folder_organizer/</guid>
      <description>What is folder Organizer The folder Organizer is a simple program built with C and some bash commands, by executing it inside a directory it will group the files sharing the same extension together in sub-directories.
THE CODE system Before we start, you should know what the system function is in C, the system function takes a command, im my case on &amp;ldquo;UBUNUTU&amp;rdquo; it&amp;rsquo;s a bash command, and execute it. For example system(&amp;ldquo;mkdir /home/example/games&amp;rdquo;), creates a games directory in /home/example.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming Languages Part A</title>
      <link>/posts/programming_languages/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/programming_languages/</guid>
      <description>Introduction About the blog Hi there, in this blog I will talk about a course called &amp;ldquo;Programming Languages Part A&amp;rdquo;, the course has the purpose of teaching you the most relevant ideas of functional programming, we will use a language called &amp;ldquo;SML&amp;rdquo;, it&amp;rsquo;s a very simple language and will let us focus on the concepts of functional programming. But I won&amp;rsquo;t talk about everything in the course and every topic that the course covers, I will share with you the parts that are the most important and specific to functional programming.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS50 review</title>
      <link>/posts/cs50/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/cs50/</guid>
      <description>Blog-CS50-Recap &amp;amp; Final Project Hi there, this blog is about what I learned in cs50 and my final project.
What is CS50? Among all programming courses, maybe cs50 is the most popular, especially for beginners, in 10 weeks you will learn different topics from Scratch to C, python, SQL, frontend, and backend, you have to solve some challenging problems every week, and at the end of the course, you have to create a final project.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
